Britain's refusal to remain in the EU is an earthquake that shakes the EU as we know it.
Since 2005, France, then the Netherlands, and then Greece...
Everytime the peoples of Europe are asked about the projects of the European Union, the answer is 'No',
whatever the pressure that is exerted on them, whatever the mobilization of the mediacrats and the political systems in each country.
It is time that we draw a lesson.
Although it is plain that the EU is failing, it is also plain that the situation is dangerous in many respects.
We must deal with these dangers, nationalism and the opposition between the peoples of Europe in particular,
because they're Europe's most visible results.
We need to clearly understand what is going on and take some time to think about it.
It's not because the peoples of Europe refused these projects that they refuse peace, unity and good relationships.
They refused the Europe of the well-off, the Europe of the cold-hearted members of the European Commission.
They refused Troïkas and proconsuls that organize the plundering of countries whenever the Commission decides it.
The list could go on and on.
All things considered, they refused the fact that there is no tax harmonization and no social harmonization.
We have to tell it like it is, the European Union is the El Khomry law (French Labor law),
it is the disorganization of public services, it is the commodification of everything,
and it is the fact that the rich, the millionaires and their privileges are given preference.
It is therefore normal that people, who only have one life and who would like to live it with dignity, say 'no' to such an organization.
To summarize, this Europe failed, and this Europe is that of the German government.
For years, treaty after treaty, meeting after meeting,
thanks to the incomprehensible submission for example of the French governments of Mr Sarkozy and Mr Hollande
who both reneged the vote of the French people
the German government has implemented a policy that suited its interests, which are different from the interests of Europe.
It is therefore this capitalist Europe, this Europe of the German government that failed, nothing else.
Nothing else... provided that we face problems, of course.
I think Brexit is a great opportunity for France to come forward again with brand new methods.
This requires that we exit the current treaties, of course. Don't tell me we cannot do it!
I know and I alerted the public opinion that the five presidents of Europe,
that is, the presidents of the ECB, of the Commission, of the European Parliament and of the Eurogroup are preparing a new European treaty.
They have been working for more than 6 months.
It is time to lift the veil on this treaty and to have a public debate on this issue,
so that those who, like me, want to assert the interests of their people and their country may be listened to.
All in all, if we let things run their course, we will only have the choice between changing Europe or leaving Europe.
This is what I want to say to the rest of the heads of European governments:
Europe, we must change it or leave it!